Guide to the Lawrence Chesterfield Bryant papers, 1865-1977, bulk 1942-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lawrence Chesterfield Bryant papers 1865-1977, bulk 1942-1977
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bryant, Lawrence Chesterfield.
3.2 linear feet Extent: 30 Items
University professor, minister, academic dean, and chairman of the Guidance Dept. and Professor of Education at South Carolina State College. Collection contains thirty bound volumes of letters, documents, business records, research work, financial and legal papers, writings, and various other papers assembled by Bryant. Most correspondence dates since 1968 and is personal in nature. Writings and other materials deal with his career, the compilation of his memoirs, and his positions at S.C. State College. Included are the records of his genealogical research on lives of African American South Carolina legislators, and materials relating to politics and voting in Southern states. Dr. Bryant graduated from Shaw University in 1940 and received several more advanced degrees at other institutions.
RL.00168
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lawrence Chesterfield Bryant Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1971.
Biographical Note
Born on February 16, 1916 in a rural community in Nash County, N.C. to Emmitt Bryant and Hattie Cooper, Dr. Bryant graduated from Shaw University with a B.S. degree in 1940 in Biology and Chemistry. In 1947, he entered Howard University, receiving a Bachelor of Divinity degree in Religion in 1950. In 1951 he received an M.A. degree from New York University, and became the first African American to receive a doctorate in education from the University of Virginia in 1959. He served as pastor at First Baptist Church in Harrisburg, Virginia. He also taught at Virginia Theological Seminary and College in Lynchburg, Virginia, then went on to become professor of education at Jackson College in Jackson, Mississippi; dean and professor of education at Florida Memorial College; and professor of education at South Carolina State University from 1960 to 1986. In 2005 he was awarded the South Carolina Silver Crescent Award for his research on African American legislators and his contributions to state education programs. He passed away in Orangeburg, S.C. June 8, 2010.
Collection Overview
Collection contains thirty bound volumes of letters, documents, business records, research work, financial and legal papers, writings, and various other papers assembled by Bryant. Most correspondence dates since 1968 and is personal in nature. Writings and other materials deal with his career, the compilation of his memoirs, and his position at S.C. State College. Included are the records of his genealogical research on lives of African American South Carolina legislators, and materials relating to politics and voting in Southern states.
Subject Headings
Bryant, Lawrence Chesterfield, 1916-2010; Shaw University; South Carolina State College; African American politicians -- Southen States; African Americans -- Education; African Americans -- Genealogy; African Americans -- Suffrage -- South Carolina; South Carolina. Legislature; South Carolina -- Politics -- 20th century; Southern States -- Politics -- 20th century
Contents of the Collection
- Lawrence Chesterfield Bryant papers, 1865-1977, bulk 1942-1977, (8 boxes)
  Volumes 13, 18, and 19 are still in Bryant's possession due to their personal nature. Collection includes bound volumes of personal correspondence, genealogical records, financial papers, and other professional and personal materials.
  - Volumes 1-4, 1941-1971 (Box 1)
    Letters, documents, and records of Lawrence C. Bryant.
  - Volume 5, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
  - Volumes 6-8, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    Letters of Dr. Lawrence C. Bryant.
  - Volume 9, 1963-1971 (Box 3)
  - Volumes 10-11, 1963-1971 (Box 3)
    Letters of Bryant families.
  - Volume 12, 1963-1971 (Box 3)
    Letters of Sills-Cooper families.
  - Volume 14, 1865-1971 (Box 4)
    Guidance, religious, junior college material.
  - Volume 15, 1865-1971 (Box 4)
    Genealogy and history.
  - Volume 16, 1865-1971 (Box 4)
    Income taxes, business.
  - Volume 17, 1865-1971 (Box 4)
    Business papers.
  - Volume 20, 1963-1974 (Box 5)
    Primarily family letters and cards.
  - Volume 21, 1963-1974 (Box 5)
    Committees, assignments, letters, retirement cards, pictures.
  - Volume 22, 1963-1974 (Box 5)
    Letters and insurance papers.
  - Volume 23, 1963-1974 (Box 5)
    Personal letters, mostly from relatives.
  - Volume 24, 1973-1974 (Box 5)
    Carbon copies of letters.
  - Volume 25, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    Business papers, contracts, letters, copyright forms, and committee assignment.
  - Volume 26, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    Letters by Dr. Lawrence C. Bryant.
  - Volume 27, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    Letters and miscellaneous papers of Dr. Lawrence Bryant.
  - Volume 28, 1974-1975 (Box 6)
    Copies of letters and miscellaneous papers.
  - Volume 29, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
  - Volume 30, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
    Copies of letters, business papers by Dr. Lawrence C. Bryant.
  - Volume 31, 1952-1967 (Box 8)
    Letters from relatives of Dr. Lawrence Bryant.
  - Volumes 32-33, 1952-1967 (Box 8)
    Letters, documents, and business records of Dr. Lawrence C. Bryant.